[Music]
only about one in four people have heard
of campylobacter compared to 90 percent
familiar with salmonella
although the incidence of these two
gastrointestinal infections is amazingly
high affecting more than a million
americans every year
it is outranked
by the incidence of a bug even fewer
people have likely heard of x-pac
meaning outside of the intestines like
as in causing bladder infections
pathogenic meaning disease-causing e
coli resulting in millions of infections
annually
multiple lines of evidence indicate
poultry
may be a major food animal reservoir for
bacteria that cause urinary tract
infections in people as i explored about
five years ago
this is based not only on studies
showing these kinds of e coli from
commercial chicken meat and eggs can
cause blood infections brain infections
and urinary tract infections in mouse
models
studies on women with multi-drug
resistant urinary tract infections do
report significantly more frequent
retail chicken consumption similarly
elderly chicken eaters were
significantly more likely to have cipro
resistant bladder infections compared to
those
eating no chicken at all pork was also
associated with increased risk but not
beef
there have been few observed
associations between beef cattle or
retail beef and human expect infections
suggesting that beef cattle are not a
reservoir for human bladder infections
whereas in chickens
of the up to 90 percent of chicken
carcasses harboring e coli about one in
five isolates tested had the potential
to cause urinary tract infections
what about eggs we know retail chicken
meat is contaminated with expect
isolates that resemble the strains that
cause human infections but what about
retail chicken eggs
instead of one in five being expect in
chicken meat it was more like just one
in 20 among eggs
closer to down around pork or beef
levels
researchers are so sure that chicken is
the primary reservoir that when they
find the same kind of strain in a
vegetarian they interpret that as people
saying they're vegetarian but actually
eating some chicken or evidence of human
to human transmission or even
shopping cart to human transmission
remember how most people fail to
sanitize their hands after picking up a
package of poultry in the grocery store
and so then even a shopper who's not
purchasing poultry could still be
exposed to poultry contamination pushing
the same cart after them
it's difficult to estimate how much
expect exchange can be attributed to
person-to-person contact after a chicken
consumer's rectum has been colonized
researchers went swabbing around public
restrooms to try to quantify the risk a
thousand samples from 56 public
restrooms and 33 establishments they
found lots of evidence of e coli in
general particularly in public park
restrooms and fast food joints more than
gas stations which surprised me but this
was really surprising women's rooms were
worse than men's
but only about one percent of the
samples they took were positive for
expec bacteria
though they were recovered from
non-toilet associated sites that were
not
visibly contaminated so one might touch
with bare hands after like turning the
faucet off after you've washed your
hands so the risk may not be fully
eliminated by careful hand washing or
avoidance of fecal appearing debris
though that's probably a good idea to
avoid anyway
and using hand sanitizers after exiting
the restroom not to mention in the meat
aisle after touching a package of
poultry may offer additional protection
what proportion of the 7 million bladder
infections every year in the u.s are due
to chicken meat like if no more chicken
were consumed
how many e coli utis would be prevented
how much would the prevalence decline
it's hard to tell because the time lag
between the acquisition and asymptomatic
colonization of the intestine with an
expec organism and
the development of an infection so you
eat some contaminated chicken today and
the uti causing expect bacteria may hang
out in your colon for months before
making an appearance making its way into
your bladder and triggering an infection
the reason we know it can take that long
is by studying the intestinal population
dynamics of uti causing e coli between
partners
increased rectum to rectum transfers
might be explained by the high levels of
e coli present in the urine of an
infected woman
which could then be transferred over
depending on
certain intimate practices
bottom line there's compelling evidence
that retail meat particularly poultry
serves as an important reservoir for
human exposure to antibiotic resistant e
coli that is causing utis urinary tract
infections thus instead of just utis
maybe we should call them foodborne utis
or
footies or maybe pronounced futi's
sure we could decrease the burden of
these food-borne bladder infections by
developing some sort of expect vaccine
or
we could just cut down our contact with
fresher frozen poultry
no harm
no foul
[Music]
foreign